A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers 1921-1998
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
001
The papers are 363 cu. ft. in extent.
Lewis F. Powell, Jr.
Administrative Information
Access
By terms of the donor agreement, researches must obtain permission of the archivist before doing research in the case files from the Supreme Court or Court of Appeals portions of the papers. Additionally, portions of the Family Papers series are closed or require special permission for access and use. Specific terms of access are available from the Powell Archives or from its World Wide Web site.
Provenance
The portions of these papers, including personal and family correspondence, created prior to Lewis F. Powell, Jr.'s joining the Supreme Court in 1972 were stored in his Hunton & Williams law firm office in the Electric Building in Richmond, Virginia or in that firm's storage facility known as the Presbyterian Building. Most of these pre-court papers were deposited at the Virginia Historical Society in August 1983.
In 1988, Justice Powell authorized the writing of his biography by University of Virginia (UVA) law professor John C. Jeffries Jr. In December 1989, Powell announced his decision to leave his papers to Washington and Lee University (W & L) to be housed in a specially constructed facility at the School of Law. Before going to W & L, however, personal and professional papers, which had been on deposit at the Virginia Historical Society, along with selected Supreme Court files, were transferred to the UVA School of Law's Special Collections department, for use in Professor Jeffries' biography. At Powell's request, the papers were housed there in courtesy storage for four years. Only Jeffries and his research assistants were allowed access to the papers during this period.
Papers from Powell's tenure on the Supreme Court (1972-1987) were stored in his chambers and in a storage room in the court building. In the Spring of 1989, as part of the project mentioned above, Professor Jeffries was allowed to have selected files (which were, for the most part, files of cases in which Powell wrote the Court opinion or a dissenting opinion) shipped to the UVA Law Library. Most of the Court files not chosen by Jeffries were shipped to W & L on March 4, 1992.
Powell's son, Lewis F. Powell III, located ten bound volumes of his father' s law school notes in a Hunton & Williams storage facility in the late 1980's. These volumes were kept in Lewis III's Hunton & Williams office until February 1991 when they were shipped to Professor Jeffries at the UVA law school. He, in turn, sent them to the W & L law school when he had finished with them.
The papers held in courtesy storage at UVA were moved to W & L in two shipments: September 8, 1992, and August 31, 1993. Subsequently some small additions have been mailed from the court to W & L.
On December 3, 1996, all Powell papers remaining at the Supreme Court were shipped to Washington and Lee School of Law in anticipation of the January 7, 1997 closing of Justice Powell's Supreme Court chambers. This shipment of 210 cubic feet of materials included: 110 cubic feet of papers; the Powell chambers' library; fine art; photographs; awards; and artifacts (including Justice Powell's Supreme Court bench chair). Most of these papers are from after Powell's 1987 retirement from the Supreme Court and include extensive documentation of Powell's work as an extra judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals. Approximately three feet of these papers came from Justice and Mrs. Powell's Washington apartment. In February 1999, shortly after the chambers closing, a final 16 cu. ft. of materials were transferred from the Supreme Court. Of this accession, 12 ft. were records and the remaining 4 ft. were artifacts.
The papers resided at W & L School of Law under a deposit agreement with Justice Powell. They were opened to researchers under the terms of this deposit agreement in April 1994. Following the 1998 death of Justice Powell, title to the papers passed to the School of Law by terms of his will.
In May 1999, approximately 35 cu. ft. of books, papers, photographs, and artifacts from Justice Powell's Richmond, Virginia home were transferred to the Powell Archives. Artifacts from Powell's student days at W & L and from his military service were included in this accession.
Biographical/Historical Information
LEWIS F. POWELL, JR. CHRONOLOGY
1907 Sept. 19, Born, Suffolk, Virginia
1925 B.S. magna cum laude, Washington & Lee University
1931 LL.B, Washington & Lee University; Admitted to Virginia Bar
1932 LL.M, Harvard Law School; Joined Richmond Law Firm of Christian, Barton & Parker
1935 Joined Richmond law firm of Hunton, Williams, Anderson, Gay & Moore
1936 Married Josephine Pierce Rucker
1938 Jan.1, Became partner of Hunton, Williams; July 1 Josephine McRae (Jody) Powell born
1938-1941 Instructor in economics, Evening School of Business, University of Richmond
1940 Sept. 19, Ann Pendleton (Penny) Powell born
1941 Elected Chairman, Junior Bar Conference, American Bar Association
1942 Volunteered for service in Army Air Forces
1946 Discharged from Army with rank of colonel; resumed practice at Hunton, Williams
1947 July 1, Mary Lewis Gwathmey (Molly) Powell born
1947-1948 Chairman, Richmond Charter Commission
1948-1949 President, Richmond Bar Association
1948-1952 Special Assistant to the Attorney General re Selective Service
1950 Joined Richmond School Board
1952 Sept. 14, Lewis F. Powell, III born
1952-1961 Chairman, Richmond School Board
1954 June 1 Became senior, named partner of Hunton, Williams, Gay, Moore & Powell
1958 Member of American Bar Association delegation to Soviet Union
1961-1969 Member of Virginia State Board of Education
1962 Represented Albemarle Paper Manufacturing in Acquisition of Ethyl Corporation
1964-1965 President, American Bar Association
1965-1966 Member, National Advisory Committee on Legal Services to the Poor
1965-1967 Member, President's Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice
1967-1968 Member, Virginia Constitutional Revision Commission
1969-1970 Member, Blue Ribbon Defense Panel; President, American College of Trial Lawyers
1969-1971 President, American Bar Foundation
1971 Oct. 21, Nominated to Supreme Court by President Nixon; Dec. 7, Nomination confirmed by Senate
1972 Jan. 7, Sworn-in as Associate Justice of the Supreme Court
1987 June 26, Retired as Associate Justice of the Supreme Court
1987-1996 Sat on the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals as an extra judge
1996 July 24 Josephine Rucker Powell died
1997 Jan. 7, Powell Supreme Court Chambers closed
1998 August 25, Lewis F. Powell Jr. died
Scope and Content Information
The Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers document the life of this Richmond, Virginia attorney and Associate Justice of the United States Supreme Court. The papers span the years 1921-1998(some few items of family history pre-date this period)and document his legal career; military service in World War II; leadership positions in varied civic and professional organizations; and friendships and family relations. Documentation of his work as an attorney is limited, as client files remain with his former law firm, Hunton & Williams. At one hundred forty two cubic feet, Supreme Court case files, 1972-1987, constitute almost half of the collection.
Organization
The papers are arranged in twelve subgroups. There are also oversized materials that are housed separately for preservation purposes. The first eleven subgroups represent different aspects of Powell's life and career. The final subgroup contains series of materials by form. These materials had never been integrated into the preceding larger body of papers. Most series are divided into subseries. Further divisions beneath this level are common.
1. Biographical Materials, 1797, 1859, 1873, 1942-1983
Series 1.1 General, 1942-1983
Series 1.2 Biographical & Historical Memoranda, 1959- 1983
Series 1.3 Genealogical Materials, 1797,1859, 1873, 1951-1981
2. Personal Papers, 1921-1996
Series 2.1 Correspondence, 1932- 1971
Series 2.2 Family Papers, 1941- 1996
Series 2.3 Education, 1921-1932
Series 2.4 Speeches, Statements and Writings, 1937-1971
3. Military Service Papers, 1942- 1994
Series 3.1 World War II, 1942-1946
Series 3.2 Post World War II, 1946-1964
Series 3.3 Historical Studies & Interviews, 1971- 1994
4. Law Firm (Hunton & Williams) Records, 1945-1972
Series 4.1 Correspondence, 1954,1958
Series 4.2 Memoranda, 1945-1972
Series 4.3 Forms File, 1945-1951
Series 4.4 Financial Statement, 1949-1954
Series 4.5 "Housekeeping" Records, 1949-1972
5. Professional Associations, 1937- 1971
Series 5.1 American Bar Association, 1937-1971
Series 5.2 American Bar Foundation, 1960-1971
Series 5.3 American College of Trial Lawyers, 1958-1971
Series 5.4 American Judicature Society, 1958- 1963
Series 5.5 American Law Institute, 1947-1967
Series 5.6 Association of Life Insurance Counsel, 1957-1963
Series 5.7 National Center for State Courts, 1971
Series 5.8 Richmond Bar Association, 1946- 1966
Series 5.9 Virginia State Bar Association, 1948-1970
6. Federal Commissions, Panels and Conferences, 1948-1971
Series 6.1 Special Assistant to the Attorney General re Selective Service, 1948-1952
Series 6.2 Joint Civilian Defense Orientation Conference, 1957- 1958
Series 6.3 Attorney General's Conference on Court Congestion and Delay In Litigation, 1958-1960
Series 6.4 President' s Commission On Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice, 1965-1967
Series 6.5 Blue Ribbon Defense Panel, 1969-1970
Series 6.6 Advisory Commission of the Federal Judiciary Center, 1971
7. Civic Activities, 1946- 1971
Series 7.1 Richmond Chamber of Commerce, 1946- 1960
Series 7.2 Richmond Charter Commission, 1947-1957
Series 7.3 American Cancer Society--Richmond Chapter, 1949- 1950
Series 7.4 Richmond School Board, 1950- 1962
Series 7.5 State Library Board (Virginia), 1954-1964
Series 7.6 Virginia Industrialization Group, 1958-1964, 1980
Series 7.7 Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges, 1959-1961
Series 7.8 Virginia State Board of Education, 1961- 1969
Series 7.9 Virginia Magna Carta Commission, 1964-1965
Series 7.10 Commission On Constitutional Revision (Virginia), 1968-1971
8. Board Memberships, 1937-1994
Series 8.1 Civic, 1940-1966
Series 8.2 Educational, 1937- 1994
Series 8.3 Corporate, 1946- 1972
9. Political Campaigns, 1952-1970
Series 9.1 Virginia Democrats for Eisenhower, 1952-1956
Series 9.2 Walter Robertson Senate Campaign, 1965- 1966
Series 9.3 Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Senate Campaign, 1970
10. United States Supreme Court, 1968-1994 (bulk 1972-1987)
Series 10.1 Papers re Nomination and Confirmation, 1968-1971
Series 10.2 Correspondence, 1972-1987
Series 10.3 Memoranda, 1972-1987
Series 10.4 Subject Files, 1972-1987
Series 10.5 Opinion Assignments, 1972-1987
Series 10.6 Supreme Court Cases, 1972-1987
Series 10.7 Speeches, Writings and Interviews, 1972-1987
Series 10.8 Trips, 1972-1986
Series 10.9 Retirement, 1987
Series 10.10 Calendars, 1971-1987
11. Retirement, 1987- 1998
Series 11.1 Correspondence, 1987-1998
Series 11.2 Subject Files, 1987- 1996
Series 11.3 Habeas Corpus Committee, 1988-1992
Series 11.4 Teaching Files, 1988-1991
Series 11.5 Speeches & Writings, 1987-1995
Series 11.6 Case Files, 1987- 1996
Series 11.7 Trip Files, 1987- 1996
Series 11.8 Appointment Calendars
12. Materials by Form
Series 12.1 Photos
Series 12.2 Audio & Video Recordings
Series 12.3 Scrapbooks
Series 12.4 Clippings
Series 12.5 Printed Materials
Series 12.6 Artifacts
Separated Materials
Published materials, including monographs, serials, pamphlets, periodicals, and reprints from both Justice Powell's Supreme Court Chambers library, and from his home library are stored separately from the papers. Many of these publications bear hand-written author dedications to Powell. Powell has annotated several of them. These publications have been cataloged and classified and are searchable through the Washington and Lee University online public access catalog. There is also a
Contents List
- Biographical Materials 1900-1995
  The Biographical Materials fill two five-inch boxes. The series Biographical & Historical Memoranda is of special interest. Many of these memoranda express the common theme of Powell's concern about historical misinterpretation of his actions. This concern is most strongly expressed in his memoranda dealing with the desegregation of Richmond schools during his school board presidency.
  - General 1942-1995
    - Biographical Sketches 1960-1994 (Box-folder 1/1-6)
    - Biographical Directory Entries 1961-1995 & n.d. (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Questionnaires and Applications 1948-1970 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Resolutions and Citations c. 1945-1978 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Press Releases 1964-1971 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Lists of Personal Papers 1942, 1970 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Vital Records and Memorabilia 1907-1989 & n.d. (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Re Childhood c. 1914 & 1972 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Re Washington and Lee University 1929-1931 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Biographical and Historical Memoranda 1959-1989
    - Re "Record Volumes" 1959, 1966 & 1983 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - "England's Magna Carta Celebration" 1965 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Nomination to the Supreme Court 1969-1989 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - "Lewis and Josephine Powell's Saga of December 15-16, 1973" 1973 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - School Board Service 1975 & 1986 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Hunton & Williams History 1977 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - "A Look Backward" Sept. 1, 1978 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - "Commencing the Practice of Law" 1979 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - World War II 1981 & 1990 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - "Unrecorded Facts About Your Father" 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Martin Luther King 1981 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Re the Byrds of Virginia Jan. 4, 1982 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - 'The "Massive Resistance" Movement in Virginia' Aug. 1982 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - "Interpostion/Massive Resistance" Aug. 23, 1983 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - "My Records and Papers" 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Nomination of Judge Robert Bork Oct. 1987 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - McGuire's University School 1989 (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Genealogical Materials 1797, 1859, 1873, 1891-1983
    - List of Relatives n.d. (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Family Tree n.d. (Box-folder 2/2 and oversize)
    - Family Narratives and Research Notes 1951-1964 & n.d. (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Diary of Frances Baylor Hill 1797 (Box-folder 2/4)
      This is a copy annotated by Lewis F. Powell Jr. in 1984.
    - Letter to Edward G. Gwathmey 1859 (Box-folder 2/5)
      This is a copy. The original was transferred to the Virginia Historical Society in 2002.
    - Re Angus Robertson Kelly 1861-1865; 1981-1983 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Certificate of Introduction for Lewis T. Gwathmey 1873 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - European Diary of Lewis Temple Gwathmey (1874), edited by Eleanor and Frank Dewey October 1982 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Re Lucy Ann Gwathmey 1891 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Edward "Uncle Ned" Gwathmey by Mary Lewis Gwathmey Powell n.d. (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Biographical Materials re Marvin P. Rucker 1900 & 1953 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Genealogical Notes by M. P. Rucker 1901-1902 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Typescript: Rebel Obstetrician: An Autobiography and Biographical Sketches by M. Pierce Rucker n.d. (Box-folder 2/13)
    - David M. Lea & Company 1949,1952 & 1956 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - The Tayloes of Virginia and Allied Families by W. Randolph Tayloe 1965 (Box-folder 2/15)
      This item is a copy.
    - Clippings 1934-1994 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Printed Materials 1891, 1934, 1956-1961 & n.d. (Box-folder 2/17)
- Personal Papers 1921-1996
  - Correspondence 1932-1971
    - General 1932-1971 (Box 3-23)
      This series spans more years than any other portion of the papers, covering the entire period during which Powell practiced law.
      This correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and chronologically thereunder. A name index of correspondents is available at the Powell Archives website.
    - Subject Correspondence 1938-1971
      Subject correspondence is a series dealing primarily with topics rather than individuals. These topics range from congratulatory and "get well" correspondence to exchanges about national defense, the interposition doctrine as espoused by "massive resistors" of the 1950's, and atomic energy contracts ("Dixon-Yates Controversy").
      The "Interposition" file includes letters of congratulations following Powell's January 16, 1956 Commonwealth Club debate with James J. Kilpatrick, and a never mailed twelve page letter to Virginia's Governor Stanley. This file complements the 1956 interposition file in Series 2.4 (speeches, statements and writings) which contains his never-published article on interposition.
      Also part of this subseries are letters received in response to Powell's 1971 article, published in the Richmond Times Dispatch and reprinted elsewhere, entitled "Civil Repression: Fact Or Fiction." This was the last piece he wrote for publication before his nomination to the Supreme Court.
      - Biographical Directories 1948-1980 (Box-folder 24/1-2)
      - re Civil Repression: Fact Or Fiction1971 (Box-folder 24/3-4)
      - Club Membership
        - General 1957-1967 (Box-folder 24/5-10)
        - Forum Club 1957-1963 (Box-folder 24/11-14)
      - Congratulations re Promotion at Hunton & Williams 1938 (Box-folder 24/15)
      - Dixon-Yates Controversy 1954 (Box-folder 24/16)
      - Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference 1960-1964 (Box-folder 24/17)
      - Get Well Correspondence 1956, 1967, 1979 & 1985. (Box 24-26)
        There are separate subseries for each of the years noted above. In some cases there are "general" files followed by alphabetical arrangements of the letters of friends and associates. There are name indicies for these at the Powell Archives website.
      - Interposition 1956, 1975 & 1979 (Box-folder 26/5)
      - Malik (Charles) Speech 1960 (Box-folder 26/6)
      - National Defense 1970-1971 (Box-folder 26/8-11)
      - Trips
        - Sea Island Vacation 1965 (Box-folder 26/12)
        - Pasquaney Weekend 1968 (Box-folder 26/13)
        - Hollow Log Hunting Lodge 1969-1970 (Box-folder 26/14-15)
        - University of Virginia Moot Court 1970 (Box-folder 26/16)
        - University of Richmond Honorary Degree 1970 (Box-folder 26/17)
  - Family Papers 1941-1998
    Family Papers contains the subseries: correspondence, subject files, financial and legal papers, and health records. RESTRICTION: Access to distinct portions of this series is restricted. Contact the Powell Archives for details.
    - Correspondence
      - Wife and Children 1942-1998
        The subseries Correspondence is divided into the following categories: a) with Powell's wife and children b) about his children c) with his parents, his stepmother, and his wife's family d) with Powell's brother and sisters and their spouses e) with other close relatives
        The correspondence "a) With Wife and Children" is further divided into separate chronologically arranged files for his wife and each of the children. There are also files devoted to letters addressed to more than one of the children.
        The subseries of correspondence with Powell's wife, Jo, includes World War II letters along with a smattering from other periods. The correspondence with the children is extensive. Work forced Powell to be away from home frequently. Even when working in Richmond, his long hours sometimes limited his contact with his family. Thus the letters--and memoranda--to his children fill three cubic feet. He never stinted on giving advice, whether reviewing film of his son's baseball batting stance, considering a daughter's choice of dates, or setting down after school rules for study and exercise. These letters mixing expressions of his concern and advice with equal amounts of pride and affection continued with increased frequency as the children left home for college and established their own careers. When, in time, they married and had children of their own, a new generation was introduced to Powell's advice via correspondence. His interest in and concern for his children also accounts for the correspondence "re children."
        In addition to writing to each of his children individually, Powell frequently wrote letters addressed to all of the children and their families during his tenure on the Supreme Court. These letters, of course, reported news about all of the children, their spouses, and the grandchildren, and included unsolicited advice to all. They served two other purposes, as well. Because of his position on the Court, Justice Powell no longer felt free to discuss politics and world affairs with friends and associates. He used these letters as safe and confidential vehicles to vent his opinions on social and political matters. The letters also form a kind of diary of Powell's time in Washington. He emphasized the social aspects of his and Mrs. Powell's life. A typical letter might include an account of a White House state dinner, a listing of Mrs. Powell's club activities and the names of neighbors and dignitaries who had recently dined in the Powells' apartment. Though he never divulged his or the court's thinking on pending cases, he distributed slip opinions to all of the children after decisions were announced. (He discussed his Supreme Court opinions at greater length in correspondence addressed individually to Molly and, especially, to Lewis during their respective times in law school.) He did occasionally discuss personalities on the court, and his basic approach to deciding cases.
        - Josephine Rucker Powell 1942-1990 (Box 27-30)
        - Josephine (Jody) McRae Powell Smith 1942-1998 (Box 31-35)
        - Ann Pendleton (Penny)Powell Bowen 1942-1998 (Box 35-37)
          The name of this correspondent - Powell's middle daughter - was Ann Pendleton (Penny)Powell Carmody from 1963-1992. Since 1993, her name has been Penny Bowen.
        - Mary Lewis (Molly)Powell Sumner 1952-1997 (Box 37-38)
        - Lewis F. Powell III 1962-1998 (Box 38-41)
        - Josephine R. Powell Smith & Ann Pendleton Powell Carmody 1953-1971 (Box-folder 41/18-24)
        - Mary Lewis Powell & Lewis F. Powell III 1970 (Box-folder 41/25)
        - Powell Daughters 1952-1974 (Box-folder 42/1)
        - All Powell Children 1964-1997 (Box-folder 42/2-3)
      - Concerning the Powell Children
        - Ann Pendleton Powell Carmody 1963-1987 (Box-folder 42/4-7)
        - Mary Lewis Powell Sumner 1959-1966 (Box-folder 42/8-13)
        - Lewis F. Powell III 1957-1978 & n.d. (Box 42-43)
      - Childrens' Third Party Correspondence
        - Children-to-Children 1951, 1967 & 1983 (Box-folder 43/27)
        - Children with Grandparents 1950-1993 (Box-folder 43/28-30)
      - Parents
        - Louis F. Powell 1922-1974 (Box-folder 44/1-8)
        - Mary Lewis Gwathmey Powell 1925-1964 & n.d. (Box-folder 44/9-18)
        - Parents (both) 1926-1963 (Box-folder 45/8-18)
        - Alice Watkins Powell (stepmother) 1966, 1975 (Box-folder 45/8-19)
      - Grandmother (maternal) 1925 & 1929 (Box-folder 45/20)
      - In-Laws
        - Marvin Pierce Rucker & Josephine McRae Rucker 1940-1951 (Box-folder 45/21)
        - Josephine McRae Rucker 1957-1981 (Box-folder 45/22-27)
      - Siblings
        - Edward Angus Powell 1932-1992 (Box 46)
          Correspondence with spouse is included here. Separate file concerning the 1979 death of E. Angus Powell follows general correspondence.
        - Zoe Powell Lane 1943-1995 (Box-folder 47/1-8)